Henry D. Flood Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Henry D. Flood Papers 1870-1921 (bulk 1901-1921)
MSS20859
Flood, Henry D. (Henry Delaware), 1865-1921
32,500 items
88 containers
36.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, state legislator, and U.S. representative from Virginia. Correspondence, legislative bills, resolutions, newspaper articles, and other papers relating chiefly to political affairs in Virginia and Flood’s legislative career.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Byrd, Harry F. (Harry Flood), 1887-1966--Correspondence.; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957--Correspondence.; Flood, Henry D. (Henry Delaware), 1865-1921.; Quinn, John, 1839-1903--Correspondence.; Ryan, Thomas Fortune, 1851-1928--Correspondence.; Trinkle, E. Lee (Elbert Lee), 1876-1939--Correspondence.; Woolley, Robert Wickliffe, 1871-1958--Correspondence.
Organizations
National Fertilizer Development Center (U.S.); United States. War Department.
Subjects
Agricultural laws and legislation--United States.; Fertilizer industry--United States.; Fertilizers--United States.; Finance, Public--United States.; Prohibition--United States.; Revenue--United States.; Roads--United States.; Tariff--United States.; Taxation--United States.
Places
United States--Foreign relations--1865-1921.; United States--Military policy.; United States--Politics and government--1865-1933.; Virginia--Politics and government--1865-1950.
Occupations
Lawyers.; Legislators--Virginia.; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Virginia.
Provenance
The papers of Henry D. Flood, lawyer, state legislator, and U.S. representative from Virginia, were given to the Library of Congress by his widow, Anna Portner Flood, and her son, Bolling Byrd Flood, in 1951. Additional material was transferred from the Lyndon Baines Johnson Library, Austin, Tex., between 1980 and 1981.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Henry D. Flood are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1865, Sept. 2 Born, Appomattox County, Va.
circa 1885 Educated at Washington & Lee University, Lexington, Va., and University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.
1886 LL.B.; admitted to the bar
1887 1891 Member, Virginia house of delegates
1891 1903 Member, Virginia senate
1891 Elected prosecuting attorney for Appomattox County, Va. (also in 1895 and 1899)
1892 Presidential elector, 10th Congressional District, Va.
1901 1902 Member, Virginia Constitutional Convention
1901 1921 U.S. representative from Virginia; chairman, Foreign Affairs Committee, 62nd-65th Congresses
1904 1914 Member, Board of Visitors, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.
1921, Dec. 8 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Henry Delaware Flood (official name: Henry De La Warr Flood, 1865-1921) span the years 1870-1921, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1901-1921. The collection consists of correspondence, legislative bills, resolutions, newspaper articles, and other papers relating chiefly to political affairs in Virginia during Flood’s career in state politics and as a representative in Congress. The papers are organized into six series: General Correspondence, Letters Sent, Political Appointments, Subject File, Condolence Books, and Addition.
Subjects include bills introduced, army and military matters, campaign materials, diplomatic and foreign affairs, the establishment of the national fertilizer development center at Muscle Shoals, Alabama, prohibition, revenue and taxes, roads, tariffs, War Department matters, and agricultural legislation. Correspondents include Harry Flood Byrd, Richard Evelyn Byrd, John Quinn, Thomas Fortune Ryan, E. Lee Trinkle, and Robert Wickliffe Woolley.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
General Correspondence, 1870-1921
Letters Sent, 1899-1903
Political Appointments, 1917-1920
Subject File, circa 1898-1921
Condolence Books, 1921
Addition, 1912-1918
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1870-1921 (Box 1-60)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged chronologically by month for the period 1870-1912 and by day from 1913 to 1921.
  - 1870-1892, Aug. (Box 1)
  - 1892, Sept.-1893, Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1894 (Box 3)
  - 1895, Jan.-1896, Jan. (Box 4)
  - 1896, Feb.-Dec. (Box 5)
  - 1897, Jan.-Oct. (Box 6)
  - 1897, Nov.-1898, Feb. (Box 7)
  - 1898, Mar.-1899, Feb. (Box 8)
  - 1899 (Box 9)
    - Mar.-July (Box 9)
    - Aug.-Dec. (Box 10)
  - 1900 (Box 11)
    - Jan.-Apr. (Box 11)
    - May-Aug. (Box 12)
    - Sept.-Nov. (Box 13)
  - 1900, Dec. 1900-1901, Mar. (Box 14)
  - 1901 (Box 15)
    - Apr.-July (Box 15)
    - Aug.-Dec. (Box 16)
  - 1902 (Box 17)
    - Jan.-Mar. (Box 17)
    - Apr.-July (Box 18)
    - Aug.-Nov. (Box 19)
  - 1902, Dec.-1903, Feb. (Box 20)
  - 1903 (Box 21)
    - Feb.-Apr. (Box 21)
    - Apr.-Aug. (Box 22)
    - Sept.-Dec. (Box 23)
  - 1904 (Box 24)
    - Jan.-Mar. (Box 24)
    - Apr.-May (Box 25)
    - May-Aug. (Box 26)
    - Sept.-Nov. (Box 27)
  - 1904, Dec.-1905, Apr. (Box 28)
  - 1905, May-Dec. (Box 29)
  - 1906 (Box 30)
  - 1907 (Box 31)
    - Jan.-June (Box 31)
    - July-Nov. (Box 32)
  - 1907, Dec.-1908, Mar. (Box 33)
  - 1908, Apr.-Aug. (Box 34)
  - 1908, Sept.-1909, Jan. (Box 35)
  - 1909 (Box 36)
    - Feb.-Aug. (Box 36)
  - 1909, Sept.-1910 Feb. (Box 37)
  - 1910 (Box 38)
    - Mar.-July (Box 38)
    - Aug.-Dec. (Box 39)
  - 1911 (Box 40)
    - Jan.-Apr. (Box 40)
    - May-July (Box 41)
    - Aug.-Nov. (Box 42)
  - 1911, Dec.-1912, Feb. (Box 43)
  - 1912 (Box 44)
    - Mar.-June (Box 44)
    - July-Oct. (Box 45)
  - 1912, Nov.-1913, 20 Feb. (Box 46)
  - 1913 (Box 47)
    - 21 Feb.-20 May (Box 47)
    - 21 May-22 Sept. (Box 48)
    - 23 Sept.-11 Dec. (Box 49)
  - 1913, 12 Dec.-1914, 18 Mar. (Box 50)
  - 1914 (Box 51)
    - 19 Mar.-30 June (Box 51)
    - July-Dec. (Box 52)
  - 1915, Jan.-Sept. (Box 53)
  - 1915, Oct. 15-1916, Mar. (Box 54)
  - 1916, Apr.-1919, Dec. (Box 55)
  - 1920-1921 (Box 56)
  - Undated (Box 57-60)
- Letters Sent, 1899-1903 (Box 61-65)
  Alphabetical.
  Arranged chronologically and therein alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - 1899, Aug.-1901, June (Box 61)
  - 1901, A-Z (Box 62)
  - 1902 (Box 62)
    - A-P (Box 62)
    - R-Y and miscellaneous (Box 63)
  - 1903 (Box 64)
    - A-M (Box 64)
    - T-Y (Box 65)
- Political Appointments, 1917-1920 (Box 66-68)
  Arranged alphabetically arrangement by name of appointee.
  - A-F (Box 66)
  - G-L (Box 67)
  - M-R (Box 68)
- Subject File, circa 1898-1921 (Box 69-84)
  Correspondence, reports, maps, statistical and printed matter, and a broad variety of miscellaneous material.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic, name of person, organization.
  - Agriculture, relief for farmers (Box 69)
  - American Legion (Box 69)
  - Amherst, public building (Box 69)
  - Amorphous graphite, tariff (Box 69)
  - Annapolis, Md., U.S. Naval Academy, (2 folders) (Box 69)
  - Anti-Saloon League (Box 69)
  - Appomattox Road (Box 69)
  - Armenia (Box 69)
  - Army, sale of surplus supplies (Box 69)
  - Augusta, 1920 (Box 69)
  - Bath County (Box 69)
  - Bergdoll Committee (Box 70)
  - Bills, miscellaneous (Box 70)
  - Bills introduced by Flood, 59th-64th Congresses, 67th Congress (Box 70)
  - Bill to give effect to the fifth article of the treaty between United States and Great Britain, 11 Jan. 1909 (Box 70)
  - Bonus to soldiers (Box 70)
  - Botetourt (Box 70)
  - Buckingham (Box 70)
  - Budget (Box 70)
  - Buena Vista (Box 70)
  - Byrd, Richard Evelyn (Box 70)
  - Campaign (Box 71)
    - 1912 (Box 71)
    - 1921, house of delegates (Box 71)
    - Expenses, 1920 (Box 71)
    - Finances, 1920 (Box 71)
    - Letters and data, 1914 (Box 71)
    - Literature, national (Box 71)
    - Literature, Virginia (Box 71)
    - Material, 1920 (Box 71)
    - Material, miscellaneous correspondence (Box 71)
    - Material, miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 71)
  - Census, Virginia (Box 71)
  - Census, positions 1920, (3 folders) (Box 71)
  - China (Box 72)
  - Chairmanship, Democratic state party, Virginia (Box 72)
  - Coal administrator, Virginia (Box 72)
  - Committee, Democratic state party, Virginia (Box 72)
  - Common Good, Virginia Association for the (Box 72)
  - Congressional investigations (Box 72)
  - Covington, Va., post office (Box 72)
  - Dairy, Dupont County (Box 73)
  - Diplomatic and consular positions (Box 73)
  - Diplomatic and consular positions, Vincent O'Sullivan (Box 73)
  - Eldon Farm (Box 73)
    - General (Box 73)
    - Tenants (Box 73)
  - Election laws, Virginia (Box 73)
  - Election returns, state, 1920 (Box 73)
  - Eulogies, (2 folders) (Box 73)
  - Exemption of religious sects (Box 73)
  - Expenses in the War Department (Box 73)
  - Farm loan system (Box 74)
  - Ferguson, S. L., campaign, state senate (Box 74)
  - Fess-Capper bill (Box 74)
  - Fess home economics bill (Box 74)
  - Fluvanna, 1920 (Box 74)
  - Foreign service bill (Box 74)
  - Glover murder case (Box 74)
  - Goldsmith, Robert (Box 74)
  - Government employees from Virginia, 1920 (Box 74)
  - Governorship campaign, 1921 (Box 74)
  - Governorship, Trinkle-Anderson (Box 74)
  - Harris-Dillard Hardware Co. (Box 74)
  - Harvey, Colonel George (Box 74)
  - Highland, 1920 (Box 74)
  - House of delegates, elections, 1921 (Box 74)
  - Immigration bill (Box 74)
  - Invitations, (2 folders) (Box 74)
  - Irish question, (2 folders) (Box 75)
  - Iron ore (Box 75)
  - Jones, C. E. (Box 75)
  - Kenyon and Kendricks bills (Box 75)
  - Knox resolution, 1921 (Box 75)
  - Korea (Box 75)
  - Labor (Box 75)
  - Lexington public building bill, 1908 (Box 75)
  - Liberty Loan information (Box 75)
  - Lieutenant governor, 1921 (Box 75)
  - Linthicum fishing bill (Box 75)
  - Lithuania (Box 75)
  - Maine, memorial tablets from (Box 75)
  - Military questions (Box 76)
  - Military training, universal (Box 76)
  - Minority report from Subcommittee No. 3, 1919-1921 (Box 76)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 76)
    - Bills (Box 76)
    - Resolutions and bills presented to Congress (Box 76)
  - Muscle Shoals bill (Box 77)
  - Natural Bridge Highway (Box 77)
  - Natural Bridge of Virginia, sale of (Box 77)
  - Negro company bylaws (Box 77)
  - Negro question (Box 77)
  - Nelson, 1920 (Box 77)
  - Newspapers, letters to (Box 77)
  - Newspaper articles and letters (Box 77)
  - Newspaper correspondence, 1920 campaign (Box 77)
  - Notes of investigations by Congress (Box 77)
  - Peace resolution, (2 folders) (Box 78)
  - Peace treaty and League of Nations (Box 78)
  - Pensions (Box 78)
  - Petitions, 1918 campaign (Box 78)
  - Pollution of the Niagra River (Box 78)
  - Primary election laws (Box 78)
  - Prohibition (Box 78)
  - Proposed bills and resolutions (Box 78)
  - Purchase of American embassies abroad (Box 78)
  - Railroad bill, 1921 (Box 78)
  - Railroads (Box 78)
  - Real estate (Box 78)
  - Redistricting (Box 78)
  - Revenue bill (Box 78)
    - 1919 (Box 78)
    - 1921 (Box 78)
  - Rifle range, Virginia (Box 79)
  - Roads, 1916, 1917, 1919, (2 folders) (Box 79)
  - Ryan, Thomas, (3 folders) (Box 79)
  - Salaries, increase of postal, etc. (Box 79)
  - Sales tax (Box 79)
  - Saunders, E. E., Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia (Box 79)
  - Senate, Swanson v. Davis, 1922 (Box 79)
  - Senatorship, 1910 (Box 79)
  - Sheppard-Towner bill (Box 79)
  - Smith-Towner bill (Box 79)
  - Soldier bills (Box 80)
  - Speakers (Box 80)
  - Speeches by Flood, (3 folders) (Box 80)
  - State appointments (Box 80)
  - State Department, consular positions (Box 80)
  - Staunton (Box 81)
    - Political situation (Box 81)
    - Public buildings (Box 81)
  - Staunton Fair (Box 81)
  - Staunton News (Box 81)
  - Strode candidacy, 1916 (Box 81)
  - Subcommittee No. 3, general (Box 81)
  - Suffrage, alien (Box 81)
  - Swanson, Claude A. (Box 81)
  - Tariff bills (Box 81)
  - Taxes (Box 81)
  - Times-Virginian, Appomattox, Va., (2 folders) (Box 81)
  - Tobacco (Box 81)
  - Tobacco legislation (Box 81)
  - Townsend, B. D. (Box 81)
  - Trinkle, E. Lee, campaign for governorship, 1921 (Box 82)
  - Virginia, University of (Box 82)
  - Virginia Military Institute, Lexington 1914, (2 folders) (Box 82)
  - Virginia legislative resolution (Box 82)
  - Virginia newspapers (Box 82)
  - War Department, Flood (Box 82)
  - War expenditures (Box 82)
    - Subcommittee, general (Box 82)
    - Investigation by H.R. (Box 82)
  - Waynesboro, public building (Box 83)
  - West Brothers (Box 83)
  - West Point, N.Y., U.S. Military Academy, applications for appointment, (2 folders) (Box 83)
  - West Virginia debt, (1 folder); (4 folders) (Box 83, Box 84)
- Condolence Books, 1921 (Box 85)
  Letters, telegrams, and calling cards of sympathy and condolence on the death of Flood.
  - Letters of condolence, 1921 (Box 85)
  - Calling cards and telegrams of condolence, 1921 (Box 85)
- Addition, 1912-1918 (Box 86)
  Letters sent and received and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - General correspondence (Box 86)
    - 1912, 25 Apr.-1917, 28 Feb. (Box 86)
    - 1917, 1 Mar.-1917, 31 May (Box 87)
    - 1917, 1 June-1918, 3 Dec., undated (Box 88)
  - Miscellany (Box 88)